While Phoebe stays behind with her nanny, the recovery team run deep into the bush.
South Africa, and it's the start of another season for the Ramberts.
What noise does a lion make?
Rragh!
Shaun has been catching big game for over 18 years.
Close that gate!
His English wife, Emma, has been a vet in Africa for six years.
We don't need Daddy!
You drive, I'll sit here!
Going everywhere with them is their daughter Phoebe...
Who's in the helicopter?
Daddy.
..And their dog, Taula.
The little mutt earned her keep today.
Flying for them again is Big John.
This is just one or two rogue animals that don't listen to the helicopter.
They just stand there and look at you.
Following in the family footsteps this year is his son, Little John.
At just 20 years old, he's the youngest game capture pilot in South Africa.
He did fantastically well.
Very happy with the way he's flying.
Backing them up is a 20-strong capture team.
And then, there's all the wildlife South Africa has to offer.
What do you see?
A camera.
Can you see a camera?!
The first job of the year is at Madikwe, a 75,000 hectare game park.
Once farmland, now it's home to over 15,000 wild animals.
Including the big five: Lions, leopards, rhinos, elephants and buffalo.
All can kill, and it makes capture here particularly dangerous.
Emma's first job is to take a look at a cheetah with a wounded leg that has been found on the reserve.
He was about to die.
When he was picked up, he was skin and bones.
If we released him now, he would die, definitely.
He's got to be 100% fit to be able to go back into Madikwe, there's lots of things that will kill him there.
There's lions, they'll take out a cheetah with pleasure.
We're going to just put a dart into him, and then I'm going to see what the leg is, an old break, a tumour, an abscess, it could be anything.
I can't tell from here.
I'll do 200 then.
We have to dart, and that's a risk in itself when you're darting a sick animal.
I'm probably going to use a lower dose on him.
Madikwe's resident ecologist is Declan Hofmeyr.
Morning.
Good morning.
Move into the other corner, I'll just walk down there.
You could probably walk in if you need to.
He's not aggressive, he's just a little nervous.
Let's go in.
I'd prefer to get the shot in rather than be quite far away.
He's just lying down.
Cheetah are sort of renowned as being the softer cat.
They're not usually aggressive, but under stress, in this situation, they've got the best weapons, claws and teeth.
OK, the dart's in.
It's fallen out, so I'm a bit suspicious where it hit.
It definitely hit, but it might have been under the skin, or hit a bone.
We'll give him a few minutes and make sure the drug is taking effect.
Across the reserve, Shaun and the capture team are getting ready to do some darting.
The plan for today is to catch some buffalo.
Being the first day the herds are intact, they're not aware the helicopters are coming to catch them.
They may look like cows, but they are not to be trifled with.
Buffalo can weigh up to a tonne, and run at 45mph, easily outpacing any sprinter.
Their horns make them lethal, as Shaun nearly found out last year.
Today is a big day for Little John, LJ to his friends.
It's his first capture, but it hasn't got off to a flying start.
The helicopter won't start.
Problem being, I think the battery's a bit flat, a bit old.
Shaun's not gonna be impressed if there's no helicopter in the air.
The temperature in the next hour is going to be 26, 27 degrees.
Buffalo being a dark-skinned animal, more susceptible to heat.
Soon as the temperature gets above 26 degrees, we put a dart in, they run 400-500 metres.
They become too heat-stressed.
ENGINE REFUSES TO START Is it flooding or not?
I've flooded it.
OK, now leave it, leave it, leave it.
Switch it all off, let the charge...
It'll come back in a minute.
LJ's attempts at a jump-start haven't worked, but he knows a man who could help - his dad.
OK.
OK, I'll get back to you, I'll let you know about that.
Cheers, bye.
We'll crack it with mixture closed, see if at least it gets it out, and then we can see if she catches.
OK.
I'm gonna have a cup of tea, you go try that.
Give me a shout when you start it.
He's gone down quite quickly, and that worries me because he's not the healthiest cheetah and the drug dose might have been a bit too high.
We'll get in and monitor him.
Because he's such a high-risk anaesthetic, I have this fabulous beepy toy called a pulse oximeter which just monitors his pulse rate and his oxygen levels.
It makes very comforting beeping noises.
Phoebe, do you want to come here and see him?
Do you want to touch?
Touch?
Touch!
Touch.
He's put on weight, so you can imagine what he was like when Declan picked him up.
He's still underweight, but some muscle mass there.
This is the bad leg.
His knee is in place.
We've got a very hard, bony swelling here.
Cheetah!
Isn't it, with a sore leg.
PHOEBE BABBLES I'm looking at tumour, or old break that's healing.
I can't tell the difference.
If it started to get bigger...
I would put money on a tumour.
But only time will tell.
If it turns out to be cancerous, he'll have to be put down.
Our cheetah population has taken a dive over the last few years, in direct correspondence to the increase in lion population.
Lion compete with everything, and anything gets in their way, they will try and push out of an area.
And in extreme circumstances, if the animal's not fast enough, kill them.
Which is why we're down to four free-roaming cheetah in the reserve.
Plus this one.
It'll be nice to get him back out there.
I wouldn't want to call it a day on him...
I'm glad you say that, cos I don't want to either.
No, he's a bit important.
Touch!
Would you like to touch?
Cheetah!
It is a cheetah, you're clever!
Cheetah.
.. We're gonna leave him now, and he'll stay in the pens probably for another month, getting big and strong, and we'll see whether he can be released back into the wild.
Emma and Phoebe are off to join the capture team.
ENGINE STARTS THEN STALLS Aaargh!
A bit of fatherly advice pays off, and the capture can finally get under way.
Right LJ, first buffalo?
First buffalo, Shaun.
What can I expect?
Well, we have to find them first.
You concentrate on the flying part, and we'll just guide them, and then try and get them to a road.
There's got to be a lot of skill on your part to try and get them to drop on the road.
Who's in the helicopter?
Daddy.
The Madikwe buffalo are renowned for their blood line.
Each one can command a price of up to £15,000.
Where's the buffalo?
Are they there?
Are they?
OK, there, that female in the middle there.
OVER 'OK, we've got buffalo here.
'We're just going to come up to where the helicopter is.'
Emma leads the capture team towards the buffalo.
'Keep straight on the pipeline, do not turn off from the road.
'Straight on the pipeline.'
Hang on, stand by.
OK, in the middle, to the left.
Are you showing any sign, yet?
'Um, negative.'
Once the dart is in, they only have minutes to get to the animal before it starts overheating.
The closer it falls to the road, the easier it is to get it on to a lorry.
We've got a slight problem, we've got a jumbo on the road.
So, I'm just going to have to take this a bit slow.
Bull elephants have to be treated very carefully.
If they feel threatened they'll charge the car.
The elephants are really curious and not really afraid of humans.
'The elephant's on your right.'
Declan did a bit of a barrier thing and then I whizzed by him.
'OK.'
I've got a few external factors in Madikwe.
And one of the biggest worries is lions and elephants in the area.
But personally, the biggest worry today is that Phoebe's teething.
I think I'm more scared of her teething than any lions!
'He's right under the helicopter now.'
Where he is now, run!
LJ's first buffalo has fallen far from the road.
While Phoebe stays behind with her nanny, the recovery team run deep into the bush.
This is lion country and the rest of the b uffalo herd are still nearby.
We're quite far off the road, this is probably our worst recovery.
They can't get through to us here.
The worst thing about landing in a place like this is that you don't feel safe.
It's somebody else's territory.
Let's get him sternal.
I don't like this position.
The only way out for this buffalo is by pick-up but the bush is impenetrably thick.
LJ is still circling above.
As a pilot, I've got two jobs.
I've got one to get Shaun to dart the animal.
And number two, Madikwe being a big game reserve, when Emma's near the buffalo, I've got to look out for lions, and any buffalo that are hiding in the thicket We're in the middle of a deep thicket, and we've got a puncture.
But as you can see, we don't need a jack as we've got guys lifting the vehicle!
We've got a herd of buffalo probably about 600 metres, LJ's busy trying to push them from us.
We can't see until they're about five metres in front of us.
The herd is running directly towards Emma.
If LJ doesn't manage to change their course, the team will be trampled.
With the buffalo bearing down on them the only protection is the pick-up truck.
'Everyone on the buggy!'
Quickly, quickly, quickly!
Everyone on the buggy!
'OK, they've turned.'
Right, he says it's safe.
A slight panic, as the buffalo were coming towards us there.
It's so thick, so there was a mad rush to get to the buggy.
They're just passed to the side of us.
But LJ managed to turn them away.
Right.
I lost my cap in that!
We've got to get this boy on the sled.
Let's get the sled here.
It's back-breaking work, but they can now get the buffalo to the road and Shaun's new toy.
But he hasn't read the instructions.
CLANKING Not to sure what all the buttons are about.
Whoa!
Shaun seems to have a lovely smile on his face as he's playing with the crane.
I'm not allowed to touch it.
Boys with toys.
It's going to be an hour's drive to get these buffalo back to base.
Halfway through the journey disaster strikes.
It's quite a slant and this lad's just slipped off.
Let's roll that on to a sled.
I'll quickly lift this one up!
We've just had two large buffalo slipping off the track there.
Lucky it wasn't too high.
And they sort of gracefully slid off as a buffalo can.
After that, they're not taking any chances.
We were able to get them back on, strap them in securely.
It's a good result, but getting there was not good and a bit scary.
We can lose animals like that as they've just had a big shock.
Luckily they haven't been damaged and no guys have been damaged.
On the reserve next door to Madikwe, Big John is after blue wildebeest.
Once, animals could roam freely throughout South Africa but now everywhere is fenced.
So their movement must be managed by man.
They're coming back!
Quickly, guys!
Quickly!
The wildebeest that we've caught are going to Madikwe.
Madikwe over-caught a couple of years ago and they've got 70 lions there.
So these nine are going to be lion-feed.
Ja, that's nature.
Wildebeest, unfortunately, aren't one of the big five.
They're one of the smaller 25.
So, the lions eat them.
They have to be fed.
As well as the wildebeest, they've caught a truck of impala.
All of which are destined for Madikwe.
We're opening up the doors, so if you guys just move out of the way?
On Madikwe, we've been taking off the buffalo, to pay for the stocking programme.
There's a huge stocking programme with 3,000 impala and 3,000 wildebeest.
Basically to try and create more food for the predator population here.
Doesn't want to go.
"There's lions here!
Please... !"
It's now been a week since Emma first saw the male cheetah.
She meets up with Declan to see if its leg is cancerous.
Sort of pull us up quite close.
I can't see him!
He's exactly the same colour as the grass!
There was definitely a cheetah here ten minutes ago.
I can see spots.
I've been sent with instructions that he's going to be named "Epekele".
It's probably pronounced wrong, but it's Zulu for "broken leg".
That's sweet.
No, I think that's a bit of an improvement.
I think so.
He's putting more weight on.
Before, when he was running, he'd...
When he stops like that, he'd lift the leg.
Now he's standing on it.
He's definitely standing.
If you think he's getting better and that can adapt his killing to something slower, like the guinea fowl, then he can be released.
If we think he can't, we can get a nice rehab home where he doesn't have to look too hard for food.
OK, I'm actually reasonably happy.
We'll hold off our prognosis.
We'll leave Epekele to hopefully get a bit stronger and put some more weight on that leg.
The pressure's on for LJ.
He's done his first darting, now it's his first boma capture.
Bomas are walls of plastic that funnel herds of animals onto a lorry.
The animal he's after is eland, the world's largest antelope.
Usually, they run all the way through, and they're quite well behaved, but they can turn and we've got to be careful because their strong point and big weapon is the horn.
He's getting very close there, hopefully he'll get into main gate.
Beautiful, beautiful, beautiful, beautiful...
Go, go, go!
That was a really good drive.
Fantastic.
Do we tell him that, so he grows in confidence?
No, we tell him that he missed some.
The eland go onto the truck with no problems, but one of the herd is causing Emma real concern.
We've got one skinny female here, and she's got a huge wound on her back.
From the smell of it, it's infected.
It really does stink.
Let's just inject her... in her neck.
OK, injection in.
We're going to put her into the crush, so it's better light for me, and we can have a better look.
It's too dark in the truck for me to work.
It could be pretty yucky in there!
Ooh!
Is she stinking?
I just can't handle the smell.
It's my gag reflex and whatever, it just all comes up.
It all started when Phoebe had her first nappy-change that I had to do, and I just...
I haven't had breakfast but I think my supper might come up.
They've laid eggs.
Now we're going to see these tough Zulus disappearing!
Don't pull the tail - I think it might come off.
Oh...
She is in appalling condition, and the sad fact is, I think she's just given birth and I don't think that little one is...
She's had milk, as well.
The best thing is to treat her.
And release her, cos there's a baby out there somewhere.
It's a mystery how she got this unusual wound.
The one thing you can rule out is hunting.
There's no hunting on the farm.
Exactly.
You often arrive on farms where there is hunting on it, and hunters would wound an animal and not tell the farmer about it, and so we arrive and catch a herd, and you often find wounds on the chest and abdomen.
Then we'll have to try and fix that.
This is a heaving mass of maggots in here.
Let's get going.
Our friends, the flies, have just come in and wreaked havoc.
I want to get all this rotten tissue away.
If this animal hadn't been caught, she would have died a really unpleasant...
Argh!
..Really unpleasant death.
These things just keep on eating, and as long as there's oxygen, they'll keep on eating.
It's amazing what nature can do to help heal this.
We're helping, as well.
I hope!
Just ticks all over her body hair.
It's literally...covered in ticks.
Look in the udder here, as well.
You can imagine this poor brand-new little calf having to suck these nipples... just covered in ticks.
It really is horrible.
We can pour some Deadline underneath.
Deadline will act systemically.
It's just an external drug that we put on on top of the animal, like putting flea treatment between the shoulder blades of dogs and cats.
It's to try and stop the flies laying eggs for the next few days.
It has to granulate and dry out on its own.
And the piece de resistance - this season, we've changed our colour.
We had purple spray last year.
This is now a nice turquoise.
A turquoise arse.
A turquoise bottom.
Shall we turn her around?
Yeah.
I'm going to give her the reversal, and it's a full reversal.
Emma has done all she can.
The mother now goes off to rejoin her calf somewhere in the bush.
The cheetah has recovered well and can be put back on the reserve.
He's been tranquilised for the journey to the release site.
OK, I think I'm happy.
Breathing nice, heartbeat good.
OK.
It was a huge bony lump.
The heel fracture is called a callous.
You usually get some hardened bone around the fracture site, and that's gone down big time.
It was huge, and that's why, in the back of my mind, I wondered whether it was a bone tumour.
I could quite happily say that that's not a bone tumour now, and he can run well on it.
Condition has improved unbelievably.
He was skin and bone, in really bad condition, and he's fat now.
Look at his tummy!
Nice big, fat tummy.
I think we'll get him to his new release site as quickly as possible.
The sedative should be enough for the trip.
I'll keep an eye on him in the back.
Hope that he doesn't wake up too soon.
Declan's chosen a release site which is full of prey, full of nice, easy prey for him, so lots of guinea fowl and the slower animals, initially, and, very importantly, a low density of lions.
We couldn't go to the original release site because we had a radio call that there were nine lions in the vicinity.
I might have to top him up, actually.
I was hoping we were going to be quite close.
If I top him up, he's going to be quite sleepy again.
I'm just seeing if me putting a bit of pressure on him...
Oh...
He didn't give me hardly any warning.
He twitched and then...
OK.
Thank you for stopping.
I appreciate that.
No worries.
OK.
Let's try again.
I'll just give him a quick MOT after that little escape plan he had there.
We'll just pop in the shade here, yeah?
This area here is where I first picked him up.
It's nice that he's come back to... at least where he started.
And now we move off...
And now we go.
..To stage right!
He's got his first meal on a plate.
After that, he'll have to fend for himself.
Hey, my beautiful boy.
Next week, the Ramberts catch a white rhino...
It's normal, walking in the African bush, taking my rhino for a walk!
I'm sitting on a now-awake rhino.
..They encounter wild dogs...
They're lean, mean hunting-machines.
They're pulling all the insides out - revolting.
..And Emma prepares to operate on a lion in the bush.
What's that?
Lion!
Phoebes, if you see Mummy doing this to Daddy, you go call the police.